Annie Gertrude Webb Porritt Papers, 1898-1976
Sophia Smith Collection
Annie Gertrude Webb Porritt papers
1898-1976
Porritt, Annie Gertrude Webb
123
4 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Suffragist; Birth control advocate; Author; Journalist. Papers include correspondence, minutes, historical sketches of birth control and suffrage movements, files on "delinquent women," brochures, pamphlets, and other papers chiefly related to Porritt's position as secretary of the American Birth Control League and as vice-president of the Hartford League of Women Voters, circa 1920s to 1932; as well as lectures on social problems and parliamentary law, and articles on birth control and suffrage for the Birth Control Review. Notable correspondents include Alice Stone Blackwell, Mary Ware Dennett, Stella Hanau, Margaret Sanger, and Anna Howard Shaw.
Annie Webb was born in Manchester, England, on May 5, 1861. Unable to attend university due to her sex, she received training as a teacher at a boarding school. She came to the U.S. in the early 1880s and found a job teaching at Miss Sarah Porter's School in Farmington, Connecticut. She married Edward Porritt, a political historian and journalist, in 1891. The couple had four children, Philip, Longshaw, Mary, and Marjory. Annie supported the family through teaching during the 1890s while she and her husband co-authored a history of the House of Commons. In 1901 and 1902, the family lived in England and South Africa, returning to the U.S. in 1903 and settling in Hartford, Connecticut.
Annie Porritt published articles in Outlook, the Independent, the Yale Review, American Historical Reviews, Political Science Quarterly, Forum, and many English journals. From 1910 to 1913 she was Secretary of the Connecticut Woman Suffrage Association and spoke frequently in public for women's suffrage. She was the author of many articles, pamphlets, and books, including Causes of the Revolt of the Women in England (1912), The Militant Suffrage Movement in England (1912), The Political Duties of Mothers (1912), and Votes and Babies (1912). With her husband, she was co-author of The Unreformed House of Commons (1903). Porritt also chaired the Birth Control Review editorial board and wrote articles for it; was Secretary of the American Birth Control League in the early 1920s to 1932; and founder of the Connecticut League for Birth Control. She died in a car accident in August 1932.
The Annie Gertrude Webb Porritt Papers consist of 1.75 linear feet and primarily relate to the various organizations of which she was a member. Types of materials include correspondence, Porritt's published and unpublished writings, minutes; bulletins, printed materials such as pamphlets and brochures, newsletters, notes, and conference materials.
The bulk of the papers date from 1916 to 1932. They focus on the central topics of birth control and women's suffrage, including historical sketches of both movements; materials related to Porritt's position as secretary of the American Birth Control League and as vice-president of the Hartford League of Women Voters, circa 1920s to 1932; and articles on birth control and suffrage for the Birth Control Review. Other topics include files on the Society of Friends, the Joint Committee on Delinquent Women, and lectures on social problems and parliamentary law. Notable correspondents include Alice Stone Blackwell, Mary Ware Dennett, Stella Hanau, Margaret Sanger, and Anna Howard Shaw.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1910-1976)
II. WRITINGS (1910-1921)
III. ORGANIZATION FILES (1906-87)
IV. SUBJECT FILES (1898-1933)
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Annie Gertrude Webb Porritt Papers were donated by her daughter Marjory Porritt Bield Blackall to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 1976.
Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950 -- Correspondence; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966 -- Correspondence; Shaw, Anna Howard, 1847-1919 -- Correspondence; Porritt, Annie Gertrude Webb, 1861-; Dennett, Mary Ware, 1872-1947 -- Correspondence; Hanau, Stella, 1890-1972 -- Correspondence; American Birth Control League -- History -- Sources; National American Woman Suffrage Association -- History -- Sources; League of Women Voters of Connecticut -- History -- Sources; Birth Control Review -- History; Birth control -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women journalists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Journalists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Women -- Suffrage -- Great Britain -- History -- Sources; Women -- Suffrage -- United States -- History -- Sources
Related materials in the Sophia Smith Collection include two pamphlets by Porritt in the Women's Rights Collection (pamphlets on microfiche), and a copy of Porritt's book Woman Suffrage: History, Arguments, Results in the Suffrage Collection and the History of Women microfilm series, available in the SSC and Neilson Library at Smith College. Several of Porritt's other books are available in Neilson Library.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1910-1976, .25 linear ft.
  This series provides an overview of Porritt's life. Included are a journal written by Porritt's daughter Marjory on her mother's life, a small amount of correspondence, and materials relating to Porritt's early death, including a newspaper clipping regarding her car accident and condolence letters sent to her son Longshaw.
- SERIES II. WRITINGS 1910-1921, .25 linear ft.
  This series contains Porritt's published and unpublished writings, as well as correspondence with various publishers, most of it in regards to her manuscript, "History of the Woman Suffrage Movement."
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATION FILES 1906-87, .5 linear ft.
  This series contains correspondence, conference materials, bulletins, and printed material on the many organizations Porritt was active with, most significantly the American Birth Control League, the Joint Committee on Delinquent Women, and the Connecticut League of Women Voters.
- SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES 1898-1933, .5 linear ft.
  The Subject Files primarily contain printed material and some correspondence on the reform movements Porritt was active in, namely birth control and suffrage, yet including some materials on religion, education, and the reform of delinquent women. Also included are autograph lecture notes on a variety of subject about social problems and the law.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Story of Annie G. Porritt as told by her daughter Marjory Bield Blackall": narrative (21 pp.), genealogical notes, and photographs, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photograph, clipping, and biographical sketch, 1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1921-32 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - From children, 1910-17, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Condolence letters to Longshaw Porritt on Annie G. Porritt's death, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS
  - Published articles
    - "Woman as a Metonymy," The Independent, June 16, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "When I Was Young," The Independent, June 25, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Militant Suffrage Movement in England," undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Unpublished
    - "Slurred History: Professor McElroy and the Bond Issue of 1895," by R. Ogilby and A.G. Porritt: typescripts, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "History of the Woman Suffrage Movement": typescript and correspondence, 1916-18, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATION FILES
  - American Birth Control League, [See also SUBJECTS -- Birth Control]
    - Minutes, 1923-32 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Stella Hanau re: Birth Control Review, 1930-32 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Printed materials, 1923-27, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous materials, 1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Connecticut State Farm for Women, [see also SUBJECTS -- Prison Reform]
    - Correspondence, 1917-1925 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Notes on cases and programs, 1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Joint Committee on Delinquent Women: bulletins and program statements, 1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Printed materials, 1921-29, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Connecticut State Traveler's Aid Association: printed materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - League of Women Voters
    - Connecticut
      - Correspondence: A.G. Porritt, 1931-32, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Form letters, 1930-32, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Printed materials: The Woman Voter's Bulletin, 1923-32, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Conference materials, program, and handbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Minutes, committee reports, bulletins, proposed constitution, guide for League members, and publication lists, 1928-31, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      - Program suggestions, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Questionnaires, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Miscellaneous materials, including printed material not published by the League, 1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - National: printed materials, 1925-32, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National American Woman Suffrage Association: correspondence re: disagreement with the Congressional Union (inc. letter from Anna Howard Shaw), 1914 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Society of Friends: British and U.S. pamphlets, and printed materials, 1906-31 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- SERIES IV. SUBJECTS
  - Birth Control
    - Correspondence
      - Margaret Sanger, 1928-30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - General, 1924-32, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Printed materials, 1928-33, undated
      - Cummins-Vaile Bill, including newsletter of the National Committee on Federal Legislation for Birth Control, signed by Margaret Sanger; 1924-31 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Pamphlets and brochures, 1916-29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous materials, 1929-30, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Prison reform programs: programs and printed materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notes on various subjects: manuscript and typescript
    - A-Bundated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - C-Dundated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - E-Gundated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Great Britainundated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - H-Mundated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - N-Pundated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Q-Rundated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Sundated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Suffrageundated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - T-Zundated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneousundated (Box 4, Folder 11)